this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at sc-radio.net
PC radio is brought to you by the IEEE
computer Society by IEEE software
Magazine online at computer.org software
that Company software engineering radio
I'm your host brijesh amanat and today
my guest is Vidal grow pero Vidal is an
engineering manager at LinkedIn he's the
founder of managers club and online site
that helps share resources and
experiences to inspire and help managers
learn and improve Vidal is the author of
many books including the software
engineering manager interview guide
engineering leadership interviews and
time management for engineering managers
Vidal also maintains a mega list of
one-on-one questions on GitHub and this
is how I first came to know about all
the brilliant work with all is doing in
this area I'll make sure we have a link
to this in the show in love with all
welcome to software engineering radio
thanks for having me on the show very
glad very happy to be here very happy to
be here we will be talking today about
manager one-on-ones with their direct
reports we will cover the basics
understand what a one-on-one is why it's
important what should an ideal
one-on-one look like how do you measure
the effectiveness of one-on-ones and the
common challenges faced by both managers
and directs in conducting one-on-ones
while preparing for this session I also
reached out to some of my friends and
peers and have a list of challenges they
have faced on the ground while doing
one-on-ones we will close the session
while going through this list and see
what suggestions Vidal may have for
these scenarios before we Deep dive into
the one-on-ones let's take a step back
and look at meetings in general
what are the different types of meetings
that one usually sees in the Enterprises
and how are they classified with all
well there's lots of meetings of course
there's one-on-ones there's staff
meetings all hands meetings if you're
running scrum you might have a bunch of
agile ceremonies like end of Sprint demo
meeting retrospective meeting Sprint
planning and grooming meetings those are
very common in software engineering
those are they might be meetings to
review rfcs technical documents things
like that right so what is a one-on-one
and how is it different from the other
types of meetings
well a one-on-one is a very special
meeting I think it's actually one of the
most important meetings a manager can
have every week with his direct reports
and it's private so that's one thing you
know they're not recorded they're not
intended to be for other people so I
think that's one thing that's very
different about them and the purpose of
the one-on-one a lot of it is to build
connection understand how people are
doing where the other meetings sometimes
are very related to moving a project
forward or communicating or downloading
some kind of information
so these meetings are much more personal
right and what makes it important what's
the outcome that we are looking out from
a one-on-one meeting there are several
things I'm looking for one especially
nowadays in the realm of people working
remote and hybrid is to build a
connection with the direct report you
know I think it's important to build a
connection with them find out how
they're doing
how are they feeling how's their family
things like that I think that's very
important another goal would be to
answer any questions that a direct
report might have because you know
sometimes people are afraid to ask
questions in a group setting so this is
a good place for people to ask questions
that maybe they're not comfortable
asking in a group setting or just maybe
personal to themself you know like what
are my possibilities of getting promoted
or what do I need to do to get to the
next level which you know leads into
career conversation so a good part of
the one-on-one can be about someone's
career and career progression and then a
one-on-one is also very good way or
place to give feedback because it's not
really a best practice or it's not
really good to give people feedback in
public
so at a one-on-one you can give people
feedback confidentially understood let's
move on to the next section where we'll
Deep dive into the one-on-ones and try
to you know get into the really flesh it
out okay so let's start from the
beginning if you are a new line manager
introducing one-on-ones in your team for
the first time how do you go about doing
it
well I would tell everyone that I'm
going to
schedule one-on-ones with you and so you
can expect an invite I would tell them
my goal in it my goal is to connect with
you check in with you give you an
opportunity to ask questions give you
feedback so I would kind of set a little
bit like why I'm doing it I would let
them know it's not optional like I
actually made this mistake when I was
starting out as a manager I made
one-on-ones optional for people I would
make it's not an optional meeting if we
can't you know like things happen and
sometimes you can't have the meeting but
generally we want to have the meeting so
that'd be another thing I would tell
them so I would tell them and then I
would schedule the meeting with them and
what I also do is see a lot of well
almost no Engineers are kind of trained
in how to do a one-on-one few managers
are so there's actually some blog posts
and some eBooks that I found that talk
about how to do a one-on-one with your
manager so I also share these Resources
with my directs some of them read it
some don't these are some ideas as to
what they might ask or look for in a
one-on-one right you've touched on quite
a few points that we will Branch out and
there will be questions on those that
I'll come to later but before that can
you tell me or walk me through a typical
one-on-one and is that a recommended
structure for you know is that an agenda
for the one-to-one what should be the
content of the one to one sure I think
the ideal structure
has three parts there's a part where we
start with whatever questions the direct
report has or whatever they want to talk
about so I usually start my one-on-ones
after you know hello how are you things
like that yeah I might check in you know
how's your family how are you doing I
might say what do you want to talk about
today
and so this is the point where you know
my direct report can ask any question
they have Under the Sun and I'm very
honest and transparent usually to a
fault so they know they can ask me and
you know unless there's some reason I
can't tell them I would just tell them
and I'll try to answer whatever question
they have because I don't want them to
leave the meeting with unanswered
questions and if all we do in the
meeting is answer their questions and
things they want to talk about that's
okay I think that's okay
now a best practice there is to have a
sheet like it could be a Google doc I
find Google doc very convenient and you
write out things that you want to ask
your manager or talk about
so when the manager says hey what do you
want to talk about today
you're like well here's a couple things
you know things that happen during the
week maybe you write them down some
questions you have some things you want
to talk about so that's really the first
part of the meeting
second part of the meeting would be okay
is it okay if I give you some feedback
so this is where I as the manager if
there's something I want to give them
feedback about whether it's good or bad
I'm going to share with them some
feedback confidentially and see how that
feedback lands and thirdly if there's
time at the one-on-one we'll talk about
their career career progression how
they're doing how their performance is
doing so that there are no surprises
later sometimes we don't get to that in
the one-on-one but I like to touch on
that whenever I can so that when we have
a performance review discussion in the
future there are no surprises so that's
the ideal structure for me there's three
parts
right so to summarize the three parts of
the first section is for answering any
questions the direct might have the
second is for manager feedback and the
third one is talk about career and
aspirations correct I think that is the
ideal formula right and how long should
a typical one-on-one be scheduled for
that's a good question uh typically I do
30 minutes some people have one hour
one-on-ones I think it depends on what's
going on maybe there's a lot of things
maybe there's a lot of complicated
projects maybe this is someone who
manages a lot of people so they're maybe
not even asking just questions for
themselves but questions for their
direct reports or they need advice from
their manager
so I think they go between 30 minutes to
an hour normally I think you have to
it's going to depend on what the
relationship is and what is the job of
your direct report and so I think you
just gauge it and you can adjust and say
okay it looks like we're always running
out of time so maybe we need to make the
one-on-one longer or you know we always
have time left over so maybe we can make
a little shorter but I think it should
be no less than 30 minutes ideally it
should be every week now sometimes you
can't do that because of other
scheduling constraints so you could do
every other week but ideally if you
could it would be every week for 30
minutes minimum right and should there
be any ground rules for in terms of time
spent talking by the manager and by the
direct because it's easy in such
situations where the manager takes over
the agenda and talks for majority of the
time well that's a great point that is
why I always like to start the
one-on-one with what is on your mind
what would you like to talk about so
that way I try to clear anything that's
on my direct report's mind before I
start talking because yes I as a manager
could probably spend the whole 30
minutes to an hour you know either
giving them feedback or talking about
their career or you know other things
I'll say one other thing about the
one-on-one I should have mentioned this
earlier a one-on-one is not a one-on-one
status meeting this is a common
mistake that I see it's not a meeting to
go hey what's going on with this project
and why are you late or things like that
there are other meetings stand-up
meetings for example where you can get
status of things there's status reports
people can send you so the attention is
not for it to be a one-on-one status
meeting and it actually can be very
stressful because I know people if
that's the thing with their manager then
I don't know it's just stressful that's
not to say I mean I'll be honest you
know the relationship that the manager
has with their direct report is a work
relationship so oftentimes we will end
up talking about work
you know and you know about the project
and how do you feel the project is going
and do you need any help with the
project and things like that which are
definitely related to the work that
they're doing but it is not like a
one-on-one status meeting I would say
right and also you mentioned that
ideally it should be every week yes so
the question is you know is there a
point where you know if you do it more
than once a week does it mean you're
overdoing it well I don't really know
very many people who do one-on-ones more
than once a week I don't think that's
very common I mean if there was that
much stuff to talk about then you could
do it you could make a longer meeting
I will do one-on-ones twice a week with
new hires so if you're a new hire for
the first month or two I will offer to
do one-on-one with you twice a week just
to have more touch points just to make
sure you're not lost or off track but
then after a month or two and you know
you seem to be have you know settled in
then I will go back to once a week
right and also in terms of the audience
right I understand the one-on-ones you
have with your direct reportees but what
are your thoughts in terms of having
one-on-ones with your script team that
is the team members managed by your
directs if you have the time and
bandwidth I mean skip level one-on-ones
usually happen much less frequently you
know maybe once a month once a quarter
depending on how many you know skip
levels you have or the you know the
person has I think in those a lot of it
is to
you know check in with people see how
they're doing answer questions maybe
give them some more context on things
that are going on it's not intended to
be again a status meeting and it's not
intended to be a like
okay tell me how your manager is doing
you know it's not a thing to like you
know kind of somehow evaluate how the
manager is doing you know it's not for
that
okay from a team members perspective
what is the team member looking to get
out of the one-on-one
Ah that's a great question
so team member there's lots of things a
team member can do right to get out of
it one like I said get any questions
answered people always have questions
right so you might have a question on a
policy I have a question on the project
a great thing to ask is about priorities
there's always more things to do than
there is time in the day so a very
legitimate question you can ask your
manager is hey you know I have this this
and this to do
what do you think is the priority of
them right I think that's a great thing
to get out of a one-on-one understand
about priorities understand about how
your manager sees the value of the work
that you're doing and the context to get
information about how you're doing on
your career and in your performance you
know am I performing to expectations
what can I do better what could I do to
exceed expectations these are questions
that you should be trying to get an
answer to in your conversations with
your manager so that you kind of know
where you are what you need to do the
importance of your work
you should also try to understand a
little bit about your manager if you
have time like what are they you know
what do they worry about what are they
thinking about is there anything you can
do to help them
or to help the team that's always a very
welcome thing when somebody comes and
says hey I have this idea that could
help the team what do you think you know
or do you need help with a certain thing
or how can I help you these are all
really good things that a direct report
can bring up out of one-on-one and hope
to get out of it so I think they're very
important meetings because as I tell
people your manager is the person who
has a lot of influence over your career
at the company over your success they
directly you know they rate you they
write your performance review they do
all these things for you and here is
your opportunity in 30 minutes
to you know basically make a good
impression on them right to make a good
impression to find out how you're doing
what you can do to do better this is a
huge opportunity
that if you are a direct report and go
into meeting and don't you know try to
get some of these things I think you're
really missing out I mean it's really
bad when someone comes to a one-on-one
and I'm like hey what do you want to
talk about and they're like oh nothing
nothing like really there's nothing on
your mind and they don't want to share
nothing that they want to ask me I think
it's really a wasted opportunity
got it so carrying on on that same
thought process what can a direct do to
make her one-on-one more effective they
would say keep a running document of
things you want to talk about come
prepared to the one-on-one I usually
when I have a one-on-one with my manager
or a skip level 101 I will spend time I
might spend 30 minutes
thinking about what do I want to ask
what do I want to say what do I want to
share with them so I don't come into the
meeting like oh you know with nothing
ready so I think it's important to
prepare maybe spend some time think
about what you want to share with them
you know maybe you have a couple ideas
you have these three ideas what do you
think of them which one do you like more
you know things like I think that's
really the best thing you can do is
prepare ahead right and from a managers
perspective what are some good questions
to ask your directs in one-on-one
meetings and are there any broad
categories of topics that they should
try to cover in the one two in the
one-on-one well as you pointed out in
the intro I actually have a GitHub repo
with like many hundreds of one-on-one
questions if you run out of things to
ask you know in the beginning when I
start as a manager I had trouble coming
up with things to ask people
so there's questions on all kind of
categories you can ask there if you want
to look at that list things about what
do you think we could do better in the
team you know what do you think about
the strategy of the company who do you
work well with in the team there's all
kind of questions is there anything I
can do better to support you as your
manager there's probably like a hundred
different questions there I find that I
don't need that as much now because you
know I'm able to be more in the flow
with it right like I'll start out with I
always start out with this question you
know kind of what's on your mind what
would you like to talk about today and
once I build enough
Rapport and trust with my direct report
usually they'll open up and there will
be things on their mind that they want
to talk about so we don't usually like
run out of things and then there's
usually something I can give feedback on
and we can always talk about career
stuff so when you become more you know
when you have a better connection and
Rapport I think it's easier
but at the beginning when you don't you
know you don't know the person very well
there are lists of questions you can use
things to ask them about their family
where did you grow up tell me about your
background what was it like to work at
this other company why did you get into
this field like just a lot of kind of
interesting questions you can ask to
kind of start the relationship right and
I'm assuming over time that relationship
builds and you're more comfortable right
and then you need less scripted
questions because you've kind of you
know you kind of already know some
things about them so you can go oh you
know exactly exactly are there any no-go
areas that is questions that ideally or
topics that ideally you would not cover
in a one-on-one
um
trying to think
you know I mean things that you probably
wouldn't cover you wouldn't talk about
at work anyway you know anything that's
I guess kind of you know not safe for
work anything that would be
inappropriate I mean you have to be very
sensitive right to be I mean it's a work
environment right so these are not like
your you know your friends that you're
out drinking with so I would just keep
it very professional and there are
certain things or jokes or stuff that I
might talk with my friends about that I
would not do it at one-on-one right I
think it's
the respective of the level of comfort
the thing that you need to remember is
that it's a professional relationship
and you need to keep the context
in mind correct correct so I think
that'd be the biggest thing but other
than that yeah I was just talking about
you know whatever and you know we can
still talk about TV shows we can talk
about
Sports
the weather there's a lot of like
personal topics but just you know kind
of keep it professional you did touch on
this briefly when we were talking about
the frequency of one-on-ones but you
know once you've got it scheduled the
challenges you have emergencies and fire
drills and if something you know
disrupts your calendar What's the
preferred approach should you cancel the
one-on-one or should you reschedule it I
always try to reschedule it if possible
so if something comes up and that
happens a lot it happens a lot to
managers because we live in the realm of
meetings there's a meeting that comes up
I'll be like hey look I'm sorry
something has come up is it okay if we
move our one-on-one or I need to
reschedule it almost always people are
okay with that I actually know a couple
managers who are really hardcore and
they actually will decline a meeting if
somebody schedules it on top of one of
their one-on-ones because they don't
even want to move the meeting with the
direct report because that kind of sends
a message to your direct report that hey
this other thing is more important than
you I'm there like no you are the most
important thing so they won't even move
the meeting which is very strong like
I'm not so hardcore on that I do think
my direct reports are super important
but if it's possible to move the meeting
by 30 minutes and then still talk with
them and talk with someone else then you
know if that other meeting Can't Be
Moved right I'm assuming a conflict
comes up that I don't have any control
over and it's red that same time and me
and my direct report do have control
over when we do the one-on-one I will
try to move the one one you know if I
can but I really don't want to cancel
them canceling them is really bad I had
a very bad experience earlier in my
career where I had a manager who would
cancel the one-on-ones and Not only
would they cancel almost they would
cancel them like right before the
meeting okay like I would be like
getting ready to meet my manager okay
great I'm gonna meet my manager today at
at three o'clock and you know I want to
talk to him about this and and then it'd
be like 258 and their assistant would go
like you know I'm sorry but I'll
so-and-so is not available we have to
cancel the meeting this week be like wow
you know and you know that could happen
a few times but that happened a lot and
it really sent me a message that I was
not very important to my manager because
they did this they did it to other
people too it wasn't just me but this
was someone who really didn't value
these meetings so I would I would never
cancel them like that I will offer this
though that
sometimes
you know your direct report for whatever
reason like maybe they're not in a good
place they don't want to talk
something's up I don't know what it is
so I'll let people if they really or you
know they're really stressed out about
work and it's done if they want to
cancel the one-on-one themselves because
they have some reason I'll let them do
that once they can do that maybe once a
quarter or once a year like you know
okay you don't want to meet today
something's happening I don't know you
sure you have it all I really I can't
meet today do you want to reschedule no
my God okay fine we can skip this week
I'll give you your 30 minutes back but I
don't let people do that like more than
once because if they want to cancel it
again then I'm like wait a minute why
don't they want to talk with me what's
going on you know so that for me would
be a red flag bag if someone wanted to
cancel the 101 more than once but one
time you know things happen so that's
fine yeah I was just wondering you know
once you see that cancellation pop up
and if that's the second time that
you've seen it how do you approach that
scenario
do you pick up the phone and ask him
what's happening or
absolutely you're going to get a slack
message a phone call something from me
because if you cancel it then my first
question is what's wrong like
something's wrong you know like what's
going on and I'm not even assuming it's
something you know bad between us but
maybe something's really bad going on in
their life and I want to know that I'm
going to give them the benefit of the
doubt but if it's not then they just
don't want to talk to me for some reason
then I start to get really worried so
I'm definitely going to reach out to
them and say wait a minute what's going
on
yep call it any scenarios when I went a
one-on-one is not needed with your
direct I can't think of one I think it
is the most important meeting that you
can have it's like a manager's
superpower a one-on-one me you can get
ahead of so many problems as a man this
is what I've learned you know I can go
to a stand-up and go to a status and go
to program review meeting I can go to a
meeting to review an RFC I can go to
staff meeting and people will say a lot
of things and I can leave the meeting
going oh okay this is what's going on
and then I go into one-on-one with
someone and they go without let me tell
you
and I go wow there's some stuff going on
I didn't know about you know so and
that'll happen when you're having uh
one-on-one with like your manager right
they might tell you stuff that it's not
obvious you know in a bigger meeting is
going on so I would never skip them no I
think they're very important right you
talked about how a direct should prepare
for the one to one from a similar
perspective how should a line manager
prepare for the one-to-one okay so you
should kind of be up to date on what
your direct report is doing
right like if you I mean you should be
attending these meetings or looking at
stuff so you go into a meeting and this
happened to me in the past right if you
to the extent you can you should try to
understand no kind of already what is
the status of their work right and
what's going on so and that also
prevents the need for this kind of
one-on-one status meeting because you
kind of know I take notes I'm going to
talk about this but I always take notes
at one-on-ones and sometimes I'll take
action items
you know my direct report asked for
something hey I need a mentor for
example that's a great one you know I
need a mentor can't find a mentor say
okay I'll try to find you a mentor or I
have a question about immigration or I
have a question I need a point of
contact in something and I'll say okay
I'm gonna go find the answer to your
question or this person so I'll take
action items sometimes
and then what I like to do is when I go
to the next one or when I have an answer
for that so if at all possible what I do
before the one-on-one is I review the
action items that I took if there are
any and so when I come to the meeting I
can be like hey you know last time we
talked about
your need for this thing and here's what
I found out or here's who you should
talk to or here's the answer to your
question like maybe they asked me a
question I don't know the answers like
they're gonna have to look it up let me
get back to you next week so I think
that's what manager should be prepared
to
basically have done their homework
because it's got a sense a bad signal
right and when I want to ask you
something and then you're like yeah let
me look into that and then you didn't
look into it so that's not good yes and
when you take the notes do you share
those notes with your direct I don't
because I take them in a I have a
notebook where I keep all my one-on-one
notes all together
so it's not possible for me to share it
because then you'd see the notes for all
the other product reports so it's
actually a physical notebook I keep a
physical notebook where I write them
down
and so I found that is actually very
useful it's one of the few things that I
do that's on paper anymore you know
everything else we do is email and
Google Docs and things like that but one
of the very few paper
things I do is this paper notebook of
one-on-one notes right you talked about
the three parts that should be covered
in a one-on-one how do you close the
one-on-one or what's the ideal you know
way to ensure that
you know you come out feeling better
than how you went into the one-on-one
for the direct well I mean I oftentimes
I'll close with things like is there
anything else on your mind anything else
you'd like to talk about you know again
kind of going back to point one I don't
want people to leave with unanswered
questions or doubts
so that's one way I'll usually close
them out you know I'll ask people to
sometimes I will ask them you know
sometimes you'll get a Vibe like you're
having one-on-one with someone and you
know it's not very juicy right there's
not a lot of stuff to talk about they
don't have very many questions you don't
have a lot of things to give them
feedback on
and so I will ask sometimes if I find
myself in that situation where it's a
little I feel it maybe wasn't so
valuable I'll say like
how is this one-on-one for you how can I
make it more valuable for you is there
anything we could have done differently
because I don't want it to be a waste of
time for them that would be really bad
but you know it doesn't have to take the
whole 30 minutes either like sometimes
it's perfectly fine you know things are
going well
and there's not a lot of questions and
there's not a lot of feedback to give so
you don't have to use the whole 30
minutes to one hour if you don't need it
like I think that's bad to kind of drag
it out
but yeah I'll just kind of check in with
them you know how did it go
what do you think of the one-on-ones and
things like that
thanks I think we covered a lot of
ground over there we'll move into the
next section which is around
measurements and I wanted to understand
you know if if you are a manager how do
you gauge the effectiveness of your
one-on-ones
so I will judge the effectiveness of
them in like part of it's like kind of
the quality of the conversation that I
have with them right if I feel that
we're having a good conversation and a
good connection then I think that kind
of the immediate goal of the meeting is
being met so part of it's kind of
subjective like how do I think the
one-on-one is going like does it seem
productive are they
saying you know that was really good you
know thanks for the feedback thanks for
explaining that okay now I understand
you know if I'm getting signals that
it's kind of working but you know one
way to measure this too is we do and
like almost every company I work that
does this they do upward advantage or
surveys so there'll be like these 360
things where all the direct reports on
your staff will be asked questions you
know like how do you you know assuming
manager support me do I understand how
my job ties into the mission of the
company you know different questions
right and if you're having really good
one-on-ones and really good staff
meetings and your directs are saying
yeah my manager supports my career goals
yes my manager's on my side yes my
manager blah all these questions about
your you know your manager if you're
scoring high on those then I would say
the one-on-ones are effective because
that's kind of the primary way that
people are are going to get the feeling
that you are helping them on their side
trying to clear roadblocks looking out
for them things like that so those
manager surveys are like an objective
measure and then for me more subjective
just how is the meeting going
or did they seem happy with it do they
seem engaged you know in the meeting or
are they kind of distant and not really
you know happy
with a meeting that would be the other
part right one of the challenges I've
seen in manager service is that if you
set a high bar for your team or if a
line manager sets a high bar for the
team and really holds the team members
to account you usually notice those
managers getting a lower score than some
of the other managers who might be
reluctant to give that tough message to
their team members and you know how do
you differentiate that in these surveys
well it's not related to one-on-ones
necessarily I think that people want to
do they want to do challenging work
right like usually people it's like a
game right I'm trying to make analogy to
a video game right if the video game is
too easy
then people will be bored and lose
interest in the game so if you're a
manager and you make the job too easy
right you have very low expectations you
don't expect a lot the game is very easy
people are not going to be very engaged
in the game okay I mean maybe there's
some lazy people that would like that
but generally people don't want that
normally you know people want to learn
and grow and they want interesting stuff
they don't want to be bored at work
right so you can't make the game too
easy if you make the game impossibly
hard like the video game is so hard that
you know you're dying all the time in
the video game you you can't make any
progress it's frustrating then people
are not going to be very turned off by
the game right so if you're a manager
and you're putting too much pressure
you're making it very painful you're
stressing people out they're also not
going to be very happy so you have to
kind of find that space where it's
challenging interesting engaging but not
so crazy hard that people are like I
hate this game you know because after a
point of time they're just not going to
want to play the game anymore you got to
go work somewhere else okay good moving
on to the next section which is around
hybrid working wanted to understand if
there is any difference in the way you
conduct one-on-ones with your remote
directs maybe you know even before we
get into that question should you be
having one-on-ones with your remote
directs
you should you should have one-on-ones
with everyone on your team well let me
talk about that okay I do one-on-ones
with all my direct reports even if
they're contractors I know that some
people you know they treat contractors
differently and you have to treat them
differently but as for one-on-ones I
still have one-on-one so my contractors
right because I need them I'm response I
need the work that they're doing I mean
basically the team needs the work that
they're doing right so since they're
part of that work I will meet with them
now I will also have we didn't talk
about this we basically talked about
one-on-ones with manager direct or you
know direct to manager but I will have
peer one-on-ones I have peer one-on-ones
with other managers project managers
TPMS you know any of these people who
are like surrounding my team that we
depend on to get our job done I think
you should have a one-on-one with them
too and I will also encourage my direct
reports to have one-on-ones with people
you know outside the team so now let me
go back I think your question was
was it any difference between hybrid
and before hybrid yes yeah so I think
the one difference is that I spend more
time
in the hybrid World basically checking
in how you are you know how are your
kids how's your family you know if you
have kids if you don't have kids but you
know how are your parents you know how a
little more personal stuff I will try to
check in on because see when we're in
the office I could just go by your desk
and I'd be like hey how are you how was
your weekend you know like I could chit
chat more with you right there was more
Chit Chat opportunity I could kind of
see like how you're doing where we're
totally remote there's less opportunity
so I will spend more time
in the hybrid case doing that in person
it wasn't as necessary because I kind of
already knew
some of those just by
running into in the hallway
yep and flipping it slightly are there
different challenges of the manager is
remote
I think that not really I think you know
can ban I mean it's manager can manage
remote just like the direct can be
remote the manager can be remote I think
the only challenges happen when you have
a situation where
you have a bunch of people
this would happen before we have a bunch
of people in the office and only one or
two people remote right so then they can
kind of feel that they're at a little
bit of a disadvantage because you know
they're not you know all going to lunch
together every day or hanging out in the
office so it can create a little bit of
inequity
but I think in in today's environment
which really interesting in covid
when that hit everybody had to go home
right so it was like a Level Playing
Field so it's a Level Playing Field I
don't think there's any problem so it's
an unlevel playing field I think there
can be some challenges so you have to be
a little more intentional about it but I
mean it totally works I mean there's
people who are fantastic managers who
are remote right excellent we'll now
move into the next section which is
around the pre-work that I did before
this recording and trying to get some
ground level challenges faced by
managers as well as their directs and I
wanted to see what your thoughts are and
any directional opinions that you could
give for each of these the first one is
from our manager who says that my direct
does not open up he refuses to ask
questions
so how do you get directs to open up in
the one-on-one I think you have to kind
of demonstrate you come from a place
that you really you know you're trying
to help them it's not threatening you
have to try to create a safe environment
right like if the direct doesn't trust
you right if they think that you're
there to interrogate them right and then
one-on-one is not an interrogation
meeting it's not uh let me see what
you're doing wrong meeting you know you
have to create a safe space you have to
create you know this psychological
safety you have to
really make it clear to them that you
know I'm here to help you and what you
say here is confidential that's another
rule what I want you to talk about but
everything this other one you know has
to be confidential you know you can't be
like sharing with the people I mean you
have to kind of chip away at it but yeah
some people are a lot more reserved you
know some people really don't want to
open up and it takes time but I think
you know as you try to understand them
what are their motivations what are they
interested in why are they working here
why are they on the team you know are
they there just for the money are they
there for because they want to get
promoted you know you try to just find
out what their motivations are and talk
to those and how you can help them meet
their goals I think you can get them to
open up over time but some personality
types can be difficult I agree thanks
for that Vidal moving on to the next one
and I find this quite interesting so
this again comes from a manager who is a
people manager and she basically says
what do you do if your manager does not
remember anything from the previous
one-on-one and she's given more context
she says that she has fourth nightly
one-on-ones with her manager she works
in a metrics organization so her direct
line manager is different to a
functional manager in every one-on-one
she appraises or direct line manager
about the initiators and projects that
she and her team are working on but
the manager does not seem to be
interested because she has to re-explain
the same thing in the next one-on-one
how can she correct this and make it a
better relationship okay you know what
I've done in my career when I have this
kind of maybe skip level meetings I will
ask my you know manager skip level
manager like what do you want to cover
at this one-on-one do you want me to
update you on these things do you want
me to bring you suggestions do you want
like I try to ask them what do they want
and because it seems like what you're
describing is she's offering the manager
some information
and the manager doesn't seem interested
in it so clearly there's like a mismatch
there so I would go to them and say you
know we're having these meetings and
what would you like me to present to you
or what do you want Casey what would you
like out of it and find out what this
person wants because it sounds like they
want something else and what she's
providing and hopefully that will help
all right so have that conversation with
the manager and understand his
priorities and try to align
with priorities so that the one-on-ones
are more
aligned with the priorities I guess yeah
I think that's well said it sounds like
whatever information she's sharing isn't
a high priority for that manager because
they seem not interested in it right so
clearly she's not on the same page with
the priorities so I would say like what
is important to you what do you want me
to bring or share with you that would be
interesting or you know or just ask them
like what a really good question be like
if you have time ask your manager what
are they working on
you know okay like we've talked about
what I'm working on but I'm just curious
like what are you working on what are
the things going on at your level and
then maybe if she asks that question and
found out maybe that manager is really
stressing about something else you might
say Aha and this is maybe what I can
help with you know yep it's a very good
submission
the next one is from a team member and
he says that I'm a Hands-On technologist
with line manager responsibilities so
he's a manager with functional
responsibilities as well so he says that
with the weekly one-on-one meetings I
don't have enough time to focus on the
actions that come out of the one-on-one
how do I address this should I reduce
the frequency of my one-on-ones
well that's a tough situation because
they're a manager but they also have
function you know they have to code or
something right they have to do this as
well I mean it depends how big the team
is right if the team is very small you
know their manager like you know I had a
team once that was very small right I
also when I had my startup which was you
know at the beginning very small right
then yeah I could code and I could also
be the you know do one-on-ones but as my
team grew I needed to kind of give up
the Hands-On
coding part and I think once you get a
team that's like maybe five people or so
four or five people there's probably
like it's kind of hard to keep the
coding again I know this has their team
so if their team is very big then I
would say one can you hand off the
coding to other people so you can focus
on the manager task now say you can't do
that because you know you're expected to
code also that's at some companies
that's the expectation and you have too
many direct reports and probably your
only choice would be to reduce the
one-on-ones to maybe every other week
and I mean that'd probably be okay
because if you are coding Hands-On in
the code base you probably have lots of
other opportunities to talk with your
team right I think the scenarios that
I'm talking about is you know the
manager is not necessarily coding the
manager is not in all these operational
kind of meetings with the team all the
time so the one-on-one is more useful to
build connection but if you're actually
building along with the team then you
probably already have a good connection
and kind of understanding what's going
on
so so it's you know it's probably fine
to do every other week right the next
one is from a new line manager and she
asks how long will it take for the
awkwardness to go from one-on-one
well it's going to depend a lot on the
people right everyone is different some
people are very open some people are not
there's also cultural things you need to
consider because In some cultures people
deal with people in Authority in
different ways you have to be sensitive
to that and so it can take quite a while
it depends on what is the Delta between
you and the report right between your
cultures your personality things like
that it might take quite a while to kind
of bridge the gap that you can actually
build a connection whereas if the person
is very similar to you in background
then it probably be a lot faster okay
got it the next one is a tough one so
here the line manager says my direct has
told me that she does not see value in
the one on one and does not want to do
it
how do you deal with this
and how do you deal with no shows
you know we have touched briefly on this
in our previous conversation when you
talked about making it it's it's not an
optional meeting but how do you convince
the direct that there is value in the
one-on-one
so yeah I don't know this manager maybe
they're not you know we've talked about
what I think the idea one-on-one is
right there's you know what do the
direct want to talk about giving them
feedback talking about their career I
don't know if they're following that
form I think if you follow that formula
and you genuinely want to help your
direct report it should be valuable to
them but let's say you're offering that
and your direct report still says no I'm
not interested right and I have had
people who you know they don't want to
do one-on-one they're like yeah you know
I'm busy I have to code I have to work I
have to do these things right I have to
explain to them you know your job is
just not to code right software
engineering I have a mentor money always
says the software engineering is a team
sport right so you know I'm the coach of
the team right you just can't play on
the field and not talk to the coach you
know it doesn't work that way so it's
not an optional meeting I'll tell you
know it's definitely not an optional
meeting I want it to be valuable for you
here's how I think it'll be valuable for
you but if you don't think that's
valuable tell me what do you think would
be valid what do you want to do with the
one-on-one then do you want to see it
and I don't know code like what is it
that you want because I think everybody
comes to a job like you know have direct
reports that are interested in all kinds
of things right some of them are
interested in you know money career
advancement bunch of other things right
they want to learn things you need to
find out what is this person interested
in right it's okay how can I help you
get that so I would start with that
trying to understand like you know
explain to them you know it's at this
concept right whenever you want to get
somebody to do something right you have
to kind of explain them what's in it for
them right so I think they were this
direct report there seems to like they
don't get what's in it for them right so
it's like hey what this is what's in it
for you
and see what they respond and what is
their answer to those questions
yep agreed the other one is from our
individual contributor so he says that I
have these one-on-ones with my manager I
go through my list and then I ask them
do you have anything for me and he
always says no
what should I do how do I educate my
manager okay this is very common okay
this is very common and it's not great
when you ask your manager any feedback
for me and they don't have any but
here's how you can get some okay because
from a manager perspective this is
actually very hard this is actually a
harder question than it seems because
you ask is there any feedback for me
then I have to think back okay well what
happened since the last one-on-one you
know were there any incidents anything
that was done what might be it's
actually a hard question because I have
to immediately scan my memory and try to
think of something and it's hard so
here's what you should ask your manager
instead you should say okay I gave a
presentation last Tuesday to the team on
this topic what did you think of it how
could I have done it better you know I
sent out this document last week did you
have a chance to look at it what do you
think so make it easier for your manager
so they don't have to scan their memory
if they have trouble right and some
managers can easily do this but let's
say this manager clearly can't think of
something go back over the past week and
pick two or three things that you did
and ask for specific feedback on those
items
and then you know they should have some
feedback I'll say Hey you know how is my
presentation on the team so and then
they might say well I don't have any
feedback on or you let's say they still
try to dodge the question like well you
know it was fine okay so then you can
say okay what should I have done for
that presentation to have been
amazing okay this is actually a really
good question I learned from someone
because someone could say it was okay
you know it was yeah this thing you did
it was fine it was okay but it's hard to
dodge the question what should I have
done to just make it the best
presentation you ever saw you know
because now they have to you know how do
you not answer now you have to think of
something right that they could have
improved right what's the Delta right
what's the Delta between this being
fantastic and just okay
and you could ask that question that's a
very good solution thanks for that the
next one is from a manager who says that
you usually have good and bad feedback
that you need to convey back to your
direct how do you position it do you
start with the positives and then move
on to the negative
you know that's kind of a classic
question right you know do you want me
to tell the good news or the bad news
first
so you could say like that you know but
even before I give feedback I will ask
them can I give you some feedback on
some things and sometimes people don't
want to get feedback you'd be surprised
they might say you know I'm not in a
place to hear it or you know I'm upset
or whatever like okay you know then I
can give you the feedback later so at
first start you know I have some
feedback for you and you can say you
have some good some bad you know what
would you like to hear first you could I
mean if they totally don't care then I
would probably give the constructive
feedback first and then to maybe end the
meeting on a higher note give the
positive feedback afterwards but you
don't want to do is like confuse them
though you don't want to give like some
positive feedback and then some negative
feedback then some other pause you don't
want to sandwich like the negative
feedback in between two positives gonna
be very confusing so I would keep them
very separate like here's the
constructive feedback and here's the
positive feedback
and you know which order you do it
you know up to you or you could ask them
but don't mix them because then it can
be very confusing
agreed I'm not a big fan of the sandwich
method the last one from these questions
is around a topic we have already
touched which is around taking notes
over here
the person says my company has a
continuous performance system and the
firm encourages conversations to be
documented in the system this however
makes the one-to-one very formal and
inhibits honest discussions are there
any particular scenarios where
documentation is recommended
or should we just bypass and not
document
uh the one-on-one conversations I think
it also touches on the confidentiality
part that you touched on from a on the
one to one yeah that's interesting I
have not worked at any place where you
are required to document the one-on-ones
you know what I would do if I was in
that situation myself is okay you have
to document so no one once but how much
detail do you have to put right you
could say like I don't know if this is
okay right again I don't work there like
okay we talked about this project and I
gave some feedback
to them right do I have to say exactly
what the feedback was or maybe I could
to keep it more confidential right like
I could maybe talk about the out like
maybe okay write down the outline but
then you know verbally I could tell them
stuff or again I don't acceptable there
to to have certain things maybe off the
Record like okay like I might say all
right let's just go off the Record here
for a minute I'm not going to write this
down but tell me honestly what do you
think about whatever
you know so maybe you could have that
thing with your direct that you could
you know maybe have a couple things off
the Record to keep if they're very
sensitive but again I don't know what
the policies I've never encountered such
a place where you'd need to document
what is discussed in a one-on-one
meeting yeah I'm not sure you're the
person seems to be mentioning about
performance systems so maybe it's not
about one-to-ones but it's more about
documenting the performance yeah you're
right yeah so or you know if you really
want to do that then again obviously
just don't have is you can have a
separate meeting right you have the
one-on-one that you document and then
you have I don't know some other you
know if you have a question and just
talk about it separately excellent cool
we'll move to the last section and we'll
cover a lot of ground over here so
before we close off what are some good
learning resources for line managers to
support them in conducting effective
one-on-ones yeah I learned a lot I took
this class there's this company called
like manager tools and Manager Tools has
a core section running one-on-ones and
it's covered in one of their their books
there's a couple books that talk about
it there's actually a book I can send
you a link from another company about
how to have a one-on-one with your
manager they sell like a one-on-one
software I don't use the software but I
thought the book was interesting that
they wrote it was kind of an e-book to
promote their product had some best
practices I can drop you some links and
then you can put them in the show notes
if you want so there are some resources
on that sure thanks for that if you can
send me the links I'll make sure I add
it to the show notes sure anything be
missed or anything you want to mention
no I think this has been really a great
discussion I hope this is helpful to
people I think one-on-ones are super
super important I did not appreciate
them fully at the beginning of my
manager career and now I can't say
enough good things about them so I'm
happy to talk to people before you reach
out to me on LinkedIn or anything if you
want to talk more about them excellent
Vidal thank you for coming on the show
it's been a real pleasure this is
brijesh amanat for software engineering
radio thank you for listening
thanks for listening to SC radio and
educational program brought to you by
Tripoli software magazine for more about
the podcast including other episodes
visit our website at sc-radio.net
[Music]
feedback you can comment on each episode
on the website or reach us on LinkedIn
Facebook Twitter or through our slack
Channel at SC radio dot slack.com you
can also email us at team sc-radio.net
this and all other episodes of SC radio
is licensed under created Commons
license 2.5
thanks for listening
[Music]